The philosopher Plato once said,
قال الفيلسوف أفلاطون ذات مرة،
"Music gives a soul to the universe,
"تعطي الموسيقى روحًا للكون،
wings to the mind,
وأجنحة للعقل،
flight to the imagination
وتحليقًا للخيال
and life to everything."
وحياة لكل شيء."
Music has always been a big part of my life.
كانت الموسيقى دائمًا جزءً كبيرًا من حياتي.
To create and to perform music
لتكتب وتؤدي الموسيقى
connects you to people countries and lifetimes away.
يربطك ذلك بشعوب الدول، وبحياة الشعوب في الماضي.
It connects you to the people you're playing with,
ويربطك بالأشخاص الذين تؤدي معهم،
to your audience
ولجمهورك
and to yourself.
ولنفسك.
When I'm happy, when I'm sad,
عندما أكون سعيدة، وعندما أكون حزينة،
when I'm bored, when I'm stressed,
وعندما أشعر بالملل، عندما أكونُ متوترة،
I listen to and I create music.
أستمعُ إلى الموسيقى، وأؤلفها.
When I was younger, I played piano;
عندما كنتُ أصغر، عزفتُ على البيانو
later, I took up guitar.
ومن ثم، بدأتُ ألعبُ الغيتار.
And as I started high school,
وعندما بدأت المرحلة الثانوية
music became a part of my identity.
أصبحتْ الموسيقى جزءًً من هويتي.
I was in every band,
أصبحتُ عضوة في كل فرقة موسيقية،
I was involved with every musical fine arts event.
انخرطت في كل حدث موسيقي للفنون الجميلة.
Music surrounded me.
أحاطت بي الموسيقى.
It made me who I was,
جعلتني كما كنت،
and it gave me a place to belong.
ومنحتني مكاناً أنتمي إليه.
Now, I've always had this thing with rhythms.
حاليًا، كان لديّ دومًا هذا الشيء بخصوص الإيقاعات.
I remember being young,
أتذكرُ عندما كنتُ صغيرة،
I would walk down the hallways of my school
كنت أسيرُ في ممرات مدرستي
and I would tap rhythms to myself on my leg with my hands,
وكنت أنقرُ إيقاعات لنفسي على ساقاي باستخدام يداي،
or tapping my teeth.
أو أن أنقر أسناني.
It was a nervous habit,
كانت عادةً عصبية،
and I was always nervous.
وكنت دائمًا متوترة.
I think I liked the repetition of the rhythm --
أظن أنني أحببتُ الإيقاع المتكرر
it was calming.
كان يهدئني.
Then in high school,
ثم في المدرسة الثانوية،
I started music theory,
بدأتُ نظرية الموسيقى،
and it was the best class I've ever taken.
كانت أفضل حصّة دراسية أخذتها على الأطلاق،
We were learning about music --
كنا نتعلم عن الموسيقى،
things I didn't know, like theory and history.
أشياءً لم أعرفها كالنظرية والتاريخ.
It was a class where we basically just listened to a song,
كانت حصة دراسية نستمع فيها بشكلٍ أساسي إلى أغنية فقط.
talked about what it meant to us
ونتحدث عمّا عنته لنا
and analyzed it,
ونحللها،
and figured out what made it tick.
ونكتشفُ ما جعلها إيقاعية مسموعة.
Every Wednesday, we did something called "rhythmic dictation,"
كل أربعاء، كنا نقوم بشيء يسمى "الإملاء اللحني"،
and I was pretty good at it.
وكنت جيدة جدًا في ذلك.
Our teacher would give us an amount of measures
كان يعطينا أستاذنا عددًا من الموازيين الموسيقية
and a time signature,
وعلامة زمنية،
and then he would speak a rhythm to us
ومن ثم يقولُ لنا إيقاعاً
and we would have to write it down with the proper rests and notes.
وكان يتوجب علينا كتابة الإيقاع باستخدام علامات الصمت والدرجات المناسبة.
Like this:
هكذا...
ta ta tuck-a tuck-a ta,
ta ta tuck-a tuck-a ta،
ta tuck-a-tuck-a-tuck-a, tuck-a.
ta tuck-a-tuck-a-tuck-a, tuck-a.
And I loved it.
وأحببته.
The simplicity of the rhythm --
بساطة هذا الإيقاع
a basic two- to four- measure line --
أساس التقطيع الزمني 2 إلى 4، حسب الميزان الموسيقي،
and yet each of them almost told a story,
ومع ذلك يروي كل منها قصة،
like they had so much potential,
وكأن لديهم الكثير من الإمكانيات،
and all you had to do was add a melody.
وكان كل ما علينا القيام به هو إضافة لحن.
(Guitar)
(عزف غيتار)
Rhythms set a foundation for melodies and harmonies to play on top of.
تضعُ الإيقاعات أساس الألحان والانسجام لتعزف عالياً.
It gives structure and stability.
تعطي الإيقاعات البنية والثبات.
Now, music has these parts --
الآن، لدى الموسيقى هذه الأجزاء:-
rhythm, melody and harmony --
الإيقاع واللحن والانسجام الموسيقي،
just like our lives.
تمامًا مثل حياتنا.
Where music has rhythm,
حيث لدى الموسيقى الإيقاع،
we have routines and habits --
لدينا أعمالنا اليومية وعاداتنا،
things that help us to remember what to do and to stay on track,
الأشياء التي تساعدنا لنتذكر ما يجبُ علينا القيام به لنبقى في الطريق الصحيح،
and to just keep going.
ولنبقَ مستمرين.
And you may not notice it,
وربما لا تلاحظها،
but it's always there.
ولكنها موجودة دائمًا.
(Guitar)
(عزف غيتار)
And it may seem simple,
وقد تبدو بسيطة،
it may seem dull by itself,
وربما تكون مملة في حد ذاتها،
but it gives tempo and heartbeat.
ولكنها تعطي سرعة إيقاع، ونبض القلب.
And then things in your life add on to it,
ومن ثم تضافُ أمور حياتك إليها،
giving texture --
فتمنحُ طبيعة الحياة،
that's your friends and your family,
أي أصدقاؤك وعائلتك،
and anything that creates a harmonic structure in your life
وأي شيء آخر ينتجُ قواماً منسجمًا في حياتك.
and in your song,
وفي أغنيتك الخاصة،
like harmonies,
مثل الانسجام الموسيقي،
cadences
والنغمات،
and anything that makes it polyphonic.
وأي شيء يجعلها متعددة النغمات.
And they create beautiful chords and patterns.
وتنتجُ أنماطاً وتآلفًا موسيقيًا جميلًا.
(Guitar)
(عزف غيتار)
And then there's you.
وهناك أنت.
You play on top of everything else,
تعزفُ أعلى كل شيء آخر،
on top of the rhythms and the beat
أعلى الإيقاعات والضربات الموسيقية
because you're the melody.
لأنك أنت اللحن.
And things may change and develop,
وقد تتغير وتتطور الأشياء،
but no matter what we do,
ولكن مهما عملنا،
we're still the same people.
لا نزالُ نفس الأشخاص
Throughout a song melodies develop,
خلال تطور ألحان الأغنية،
but it's still the same song.
لا تزالُ نفس الأغنية،
No matter what you do,
مهما فعلت،
the rhythms are still there:
تبقى الإيقاعات موجودة،
the tempo and the heartbeat ...
سرعة الإيقاع ونبض القلب...
until I left,
حتى غادرتُ الثانوية،
and I went to college
وذهبت إلى الجامعة
and everything disappeared.
واختفى كل شيء.
When I first arrived at university,
عند وصولي إلى الجامعة لأول مرة،
I felt lost.
شعرت بالضياع.
And don't get me wrong -- sometimes I loved it and it was great,
ولا تسيؤا فهمي، أحببتها أحياناً، وكان حبي لها كبيرًا،
but other times,
ولكن في أوقات أخرى،
I felt like I had been left alone
أحسست بأنني تُركتُ وحيدة
to fend for myself.
لأدافع عن نفسي
It's like I had been taken out of my natural environment,
وكأني قد نُزعت من بيئتي الطبيعية
and put somewhere new,
ووضعت في مكان جديد،
where the rhythms and the harmonies
حيثُ الإيقاعات والانسجام الموسيقي
and the form had gone away,
والشكل قد رحلوا بعيدًا،
and it was just me --
وكنت وحدي فقط،
(Guitar)
(عزف غيتار)
silence and my melody.
الصمت وألحاني.
And even that began to waver,
وحتى بدأ ذلك يتلاشى،
because I didn't know what I was doing.
لأنني لم أعرف ما كنتُ أقوم به.
I didn't have any chords to structure myself,
لم يعد لدي أي أنغام لأجدُ نفسي،
or a rhythm
أو إيقاع،
or a beat to know the tempo.
أو ضربات موسيقية لأعرفُ سرعة وتيرتها.
(Guitar)
(عزف غيتار)
And then I began to hear all these other sounds.
ومن ثم بدأت أسمعُ كل هذه الاصوات الأخرى.
And they were off-time
وكانت في وقت الانقطاع
and off-key.
وخارجة عن اللحن.
And the more I was around them,
وكلما كنت أطيلُ البقاء بجانبها،
the more my melody started to sound like theirs.
كلما بدأ لحني يشبه لحنهم أكثر.
And slowly I began to lose myself,
وبدأت ببطء أفقد نفسي،
like I was being washed away.
وكأني بدأتُ أتلاشى بعيدًا.
But then the next moment --
وبعدها في اللحظة التالية،
(Guitar)
(عزف غيتار)
I could hear it.
استطعتُ سماعها.
And I could feel it.
واستطعتُ الشعور بها.
And it was me.
وكانت أنا.
And I was here.
وكنت هناك.
And it was different,
وكانت مختلفة،
but not worse off.
ولم تكن أسوأ حالًا.
Just changed a little.
متغيرة قليلًا فقط.
Music is my way of coping with the changes in my life.
الموسيقى هي طريقتي للتأقلم مع تغييرات الحياة.
There's a beautiful connection between music and life.
هنالك صلة جميلة بين الموسيقى والحياة.
It can bind us to reality
تستطيع ربطنا بالواقع
at the same time it allows us to escape it.
وبنفس الوقت تسمح لنا بالهروب منه.
Music is something that lives inside of you.
الموسيقى شيء يعيش داخل كل واحد فيكم.
You create it and you're created by it.
تصنعها وتصنعك.
Our lives are not only conducted by music,
لا تدارُ حياتنا بسبب الموسيقى فقط،
they're also composed of it.
ولكنها أيضًا تتألفُ منها.
So this may seem like a bit of a stretch,
قد يبدو هذا مبالغاً فيه قليلًا،
but hear me out:
لكن اسمعوني،
music is a fundamental part of what we are
الموسيقى جزء أساسي مما نحنُ عليه،
and of everything around us.
وكل مما هو حولنا.
Now, music is my passion,
الآن، الموسيقى هي شغفي،
but physics also used to be an interest of mine.
لكن كانت الفيزياء أيضًا إحدى اهتماماتي.
And the more I learned,
وكلما تعلمت أكثر،
the more I saw connections between the two --
كلما رأيت الصلة بينهما أكثر،
especially regarding string theory.
خصوصاً فيما يتعلق بنظرية الأوتار.
I know this is only one of many theories,
أعلم أنها واحدة من بين نظريات عدة،
but it spoke to me.
لكنها تتحدثُ معي.
So, one aspect of string theory, at its simplest form, is this:
أحد جوانب نظرية الأوتار، عند أبسط أشكالها، هو:
matter is made up of atoms,
المادة مصنوعة من ذرات،
which are made up of protons and neutrons and electrons,
التي تتكون من بروتونات، ونيترونات واليكترونات،
which are made up of quark.
التي تتكون من جسيم أولي للمادة.
And here's where the string part comes in.
وهنا حيثُ يأتي جانب الوتر.
This quark is supposedly made up of little coiled strings,
من المفترض أن الكوارك يتكون من أوتار صغيرة لولبية،
and it's the vibrations of these strings that make everything what it is.
واهتزازات هذه الأوتار تجعل كل شيء كما هو عليه.
Michio Kaku once explained this
فسّر ميتشو كاكو هذا ذات مرة
in a lecture called, "The Universe in a Nutshell,"
في محاضرة بعنوان "الكون في قشرة جوز"
where he says,
حيثُ يقول،
"String theory is the simple idea
"نظرية الأوتار فكرة بسيطة
that the four forces of the universe --
بأن القوى الأربعة في الكون،
gravity, the electromagnetic force, and the two strong forces --
الجاذبية، والقوة الكهرومغناطيسية، والقوتان النوويتان القويتان،
can be viewed as music.
يمكن اعتبارها كالموسيقى.
The music of tiny little rubber bands."
الموسيقى من الراباطات المطاطية الصغيرة."
In this lecture, he goes on to explain physics
في هذه المحاضرة، يمضي في تفسير للفيزياء
as the laws of harmony between these strings;
كما قوانين الإنسجام بين هذه الأوتار،
chemistry, as the melodies you can play on these strings;
الكيمياء، كما الألحان التي يمكنك أن تلعبها على هذه الأوتار،
and he states that the universe is a "symphony of strings."
ويقول بأن الكون هو "لحن موسيقي للأوتار".
These strings dictate the universe;
تصدرُ هذه الأوتار أوأمرها على الكون،
they make up everything we see and everything we know.
وتنتجُ كل ما نرى ونعرف.
They're musical notes,
إنها درجات وسلالم موسيقية،
but they make us what we are and they hold us together.
لكنها تجعلنا كما نحنُ عليه، وتبقينا متماسكين معًا.
So you see,
لذلك فكما ترى،
everything is music.
كل شيء هو موسيقي.
(Guitar)
(عزف غيتار)
When I look at the world,
عندما أنظر إلى العالم
I see music all around us.
أرى الموسيقى حولنا في كل مكان.
When I look at myself,
عندما أنظر إلى نفسي،
I see music.
أرى موسيقى.
And my life has been defined by music.
وتم تحديد حياتي من قبل الموسيقى.
I found myself through music.
وجدت نفسي من خلال الموسيقى.
Music is everywhere,
الموسيقى في كل مكان،
and it is in everything.
وفي كل شيء.
And it changes and it builds
وهي تغيرُ وتبني
and it diminishes.
وتختفي.
But it's always there,
ولكنها دومًا هناك،
supporting us,
تدعمنا،
connecting us to each other
تربطُ بعضنا ببعض
and showing us the beauty of the universe.
وترينا جمال الكون.
So if you ever feel lost,
لذلك، إذا أحسست يومًا بالضياع،
stop and listen for your song.
توقف واستمع إلى أغنيتك.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)